Guide to the Bicentennial Schlock Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bicentennial Schlock Collection
1967-1977
MS 1262
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.5
(13 boxes)
A collection of objects and packaging for commercial products celebrating the United States Bicentennial in 1976. These items were assembled as a course project for Jesse Lemisch's American Studies class at SUNY/Buffalo in the spring of 1976 and exhibited in 1976 and 1977. Included in the collection are catalogues of the exhibitions as well as related correspondence and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jesse Lemisch, 1981.
Scope and Contents
The Bicentennial Schlock collection began as a course project for Jesse Lemisch's American Studies class at SUNY/Buffalo in the spring of 1976. Their search for Bicentennial items led to an exhibit of the collected materials at Hayes Hall on the SUNY/Buffalo campus October 5-29, 1976. This exhibit was so successful that it appeared again at Gallery 1199, the exhibit hall of the District 1199 Headquarters of the Hospital Employee's Union, Aug 11-Sep 8, 1977.
The collection consists of correspondence, notes and memoranda, printed material and photographs, including photographs of the original exhibit, followed by a wide variety of "Schlock" exhibit material. The bulk of the collection is material which was actually exhibited. It ranges from paper plates and beer cans to a pair of stuffed mice. No attempt was made to keep the material in its original exhibit order, though wherever possible exhibit labels have been kept with the items they describe. Some of the items which appeared in the exhibits were not included in the collection (e.g., clock, belt, flag, items of clothing).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Advertising; American Revolution Bicentennial, 1976; Popular culture; United States -- Social life and customs; Lemisch, Jesse, 1936-
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Mail solicitation for commemorative plate by United States Commemorative Gallery, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence relating to Gallery 1199 exhibit, 1976 October-1977 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New York State Historical Association, 1977 May-June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Course outline for American Studies 200, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft of introduction to exhibit, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hayes Hall Exhibit
    - Invitations to opening of Bicentennial Schlock Exhibit, 1976 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notes and memoranda, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notes for acknowledgements, Circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gallery 1199 Exhibit
    - Notes for exhibit program, Circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bicentennial Schlock Exhibit programs, 1977 August-September (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Copy of guest register, 1977 August 11-September 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - News releases announcing exhibits at Hayes Hall and at Gallery 1199, 1976 September 28; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed material
    - Article "Bicentennial Schlock" by Jesse Lemisch, in The New Republic, 1976 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Clippings, Circa 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Adams Chronicles brochure, clipping, 1975, 1976 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Publications of the Peoples Bicentennial Commission, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - USA/200, 1976 Feb, June (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1199 News, 1976 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bicentennial Times, 1976 February-March (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bicentennial News, 1976 Mar, June (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of Bicentennial Schlock Exhibit at Hayes Hall, SUNY/Buffalo, 1976 October (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Photographs of items from Bicentennial Schlock, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Exhibit material
    - Plastic bag with 1776 flag, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Plastic bag showing the flag, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Paper bag with Declaration of Independence, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Sani Bags with Liberty Bell, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Sugar and the Bicentennial", Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Post-Bicentennial Sugar Packets", Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Two dollar bill, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Exhibit program used as part of exhibit, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Bicentennial News, final issue, 1976 July 1 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Advertisement for Simplicity Bicentennial Costumes, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Clothing advertisements, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Label from milk carton, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Box label from Ideal Pretzels, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "The Attempt to Steal the Bicentennial," Report of the Internal Security Subcommittee of the Senate Judiciary Committee, 1976 May (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Plastic flag, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Time Magazine, Special 1776 Edition, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Comic book: "Give Me Liberty: A Revised History of the American Revolution", 1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Mail solicitations for personalized commemorative plate, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Burger King calendars, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Menus and Recipes of the Great American Revolution," advertisement by Texaco, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Candy with flags, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Advertisement for "Bicentennial Wedding" at Collegeville Inn, 1976 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Sheraton Hotels brochure, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Navy advertisement, Circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Brochure for "The Adams Chronicles", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Comprehensive Calendar of Bicentennial Events, East of the Mississippi", 1976 June (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Exhibit labels (unidentified), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Winchester Arms Catalogue, Bicentennial Edition, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Disney World popcorn box, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Big Boy hamburger wrapper, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Package for "Bi-Centennial Lollipop", Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - American Airlines ticket cover and paper napkin, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Operating room cap, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Package for "Bicentennial Huggy Bears", Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Paper napkins and plates from Pappy's Pizza, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Packages for "Clark 1776 Peanut Butter Logs", Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - TV Guide, 1976 July 3-9 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Paper napkins, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Corsage, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Advertisement for "Chicken '76: the Revolutionary Chicken", Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Uncle Sam Pez dispenser, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Match books, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Sambo's paper flag and paper coaster, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Bookmark/calendar quoting Sun Myung Moon, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Button card, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Pins sent to Organization of American Historians, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Postcards of train locomotives, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Cards with Uncle Sam, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Paper "76" flag on toothpick, Circa 1976 (Box 3, Folder 73a)
    - Knit cap, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Pen and pencil, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - "The All-American Novelty Condom", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Photograph of Quaintance Eaton dressed for the Bicentennial, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Name tags, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - The Old Farmer's Almanac, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Erie County Savings Bank Bicentennial brochure, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Button pins, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Button pin, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Towellettes, Circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Toy robot, Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Large paper cup and three straws, Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Pair of stuffed mice in Bicentennial dress, Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Scarf, Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Painter's cap, Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Paper plates, "Spirit of 1776", Circa 1976 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Egg cartons, 1976; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Campbell's soup can, Circa 1976 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Beer cans; soda can, Circa 1976; 7 items. (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Roll of toilet paper, "Spirit of 1776", 1976 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Paper cups, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - "1776" Coke glass, Circa 1976 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Water glass with Liberty Bell wrapper, Circa 1976 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Instant coffee jar, Circa 1976 (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Log Cabin Syrup Bicentennial Flasks, Circa 1976 (Box 9, Folder 98-100)
    - 7-Up Commemorative Bottle, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 123)
    - Course outline used in exhibit, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Plastic flag with candy-filled stick, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 102)
    - Package for "Peter Patriot Hollow Milk Chocolate" Rabbit, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Apple advertisement, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Menu from Howard Johnson's, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - Menus from The Lite-Bite, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Mail solicitations for personalized flag by American Historical Society, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Stick-on badge "Valor at Valley Forge;" brochure for Bicentennial Histories; exhibition guide for "The World of Franklin & Jefferson", Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Paper plates showing scenes from the Revolution, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Paper placemat with Declaration of Independence, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Paper placemat "Bicentennial Observance", Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - "Peacetime" dry cleaning bag, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Clothes hangers, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - "Peacetime" plastic shopping bag, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - Diaper bag with Bicentennial logo, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Plastic bag with Declaration of Independence, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 116)
    - Grocery bags with Liberty Bell, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 117)
    - Plastic bag from National Archives, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Paper shopping bag, Circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - Welcome mat with eagle, Circa 1976 (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - Cereal boxes, 1967, 1972; 2 items. (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Pinwheel, Circa 1976 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Kite with Declaration of Independence, Circa 1976 (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Record cover for "Celebration '76", 1976 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Posters, "Happy Birthday, America", 1975 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Nabisco display, Circa 1976; 2 items. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Sign for Gallery 1199 exhibit, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)